Hi guys, I'm back and in today's video we are going to deal with one
of the hardest, most painful questions in the
IELTS reading test, which is matching headings.
So stay tuned and we'll dive right into it.
This lesson aims to help you understand some features of matching headings,
choose one effective approach to matching headings,
understand and apply steps for matching headings.
So hang in there, it'll be worth it, I promise.
We'll start with the first part of today's lesson.
Matching headings is a question type which requires candidates to match the
given headings with the paragraphs, so that each paragraph will be matched with
its corresponding heading.
Questions of matching headings often have three parts, a requirement,
a list of headings and question numbers corresponding to paragraphs.
Moreover, there are some features of matching
headings that you should pay attention to.
One heading is only used for one paragraph, there are no
cases where two or more paragraphs have the same heading.
There are usually more headings than the number of
paragraphs, so there are some headings that are not used.
The correct headings need to cover the whole content of paragraphs.
These are the most basic features of this question
type, let's analyse it in more detail in the next part.
There are two approaches to matching headings that you can choose from.
Approach 1. Answer this question type right
from the beginning, because it usually appears
as the first question type of one passage, usually in passage 2.
The advantage is that it helps us to understand the main idea of all
paragraphs, therefore we can answer the following question types faster.
However, the disadvantage is that it can take
us a lot of time from the beginning of the test.
As a result, it is difficult to manage time.
If we answer this question type for too long, we can take up a lot
of time for other questions and can't solve all the questions in time.
Approach 2. Answer this question type last.
The advantage is that we can finish this question type faster, because after
answering other question types, we can understand the main idea of the whole
reading passage and can somehow understand the information in each paragraph.
So finding the main idea of each paragraph is faster.
The disadvantage is that we can't answer other question
types as quickly as we take the first approach.
Of course, the choice belongs to you.
Each of you can have an approach that you find effective,
so please choose the most suitable one for yourself.
Now let's see how we can handle the matching headings questions.
Now let's learn how to handle this question type step by step.
Step 1.
Read given headings and underline keywords.
In this step, we need to have an overview of the headings.
Because this question type often includes headings with similar keywords, you
need to take notes by circling or rewriting the
similarities or differences in your own language.
This helps us find out the correct headings more easily.
After you understand the importance of this step, I'll
give you 15 seconds to underline keywords in each heading.
Find out differences among the headings that contain similar keywords.
Here are the keywords I found when reading the headings.
When reading, I noticed that headings 5 and 6 both talk about education or
schools, but 5 focuses on different ways and
methods, while 6 focuses on success rates.
Similarly, headings 1 and 4 both mention the brain, but 1 is about old age
or health, and 4 is about focus and multitasking.
After having an overview, we move on to the next step.
Step 2. Use skimming skills for
each paragraph to find the main idea.
A quick tip.
In academic writing, the first sentence is often the topic
sentence, and the last sentence summarizes the ideas.
Let's analyze the content words to find the main idea.
This first sentence sets the context.
The key idea here is, speaking more than one language is becoming more common.
Now on to the second sentence.
This sentence explains why it is becoming common.
Keywords include migration, global
communication, millions use different languages.
This sentence here reinforces the first point.
Keywords here are rare skill and normal part of life.
The final sentence summarizes the trend.
Keywords include specialized talent and essential everyday skill.
To sum up, we can see the main idea of paragraph A is about how
speaking multiple languages has grown from something rare to something very
common and essential globally.
Step 3. Choose the most suitable
heading for each paragraph.
Now let's look at our headings again and
choose the one that matches our main idea.
Let's check heading 3.
The paragraph talks about modern, connected world, migration, global
communication, and how it is becoming more common and a normal part of life.
This matches perfectly with global increase.
So the answer for paragraph A is 3.
Once found, cross it out to save time for the next paragraph.
In today's lesson, we've learned about the structures and features of matching headings,
the two approaches to matching headings,
and three steps for matching headings.
Moreover, we also mentioned some common difficulties, solutions, as well as
tips to skim a little more effectively for matching headings questions.
Please take note of those tips and practice regularly.
Remember to choose reading materials that are suitable for your level, as I
mentioned in the video about the course introduction.
Moreover, if you don't have enough vocabulary and a good understanding of
grammar, it will be a bit challenging for
you to apply the knowledge in today's lesson.
Finally, I really do hope you enjoyed this lesson.
See you next time.
Goodbye.